Finding Aid for Michigan Seagrant Program, Publications, 1972-2004
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Michigan Seagrant Program, Publications 1972-2004
Michigan Sea Grant Program.
0438; Bimu; 2
The Michigan Sea Grant Program is a joint project between the University of Michigan, Michigan State University, and the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA) addressing issues concerning the livelihood of the Michigan Great Lakes area. Includes technical reports, annual reports, newsletters, brochures and other printed material produced by the program.
5.5 linear feet
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The publications are received periodically from the unit (donor no. 6502 ).
The publications are open without restriction.
For background of this unit, please consult the history found in the Michigan Sea Grant Program Records.
The Michigan Sea Grant Program Publications consist of 5.5 linear feet which includes annual reports, brochures, extension bulletins, directories, ephemera including flyers, fact sheets, posters, programs, histories, manuals, newsletters, proceedings of conferences sponsored by Michigan Sea Grant, and reports. These publications are divided into two series: Unit Publications and Topical Publications. The bulk of the publications are technical reports that were published between 1972-1998.
Subjects:
Fishing--Great Lakes.; Scuba diving--Michigan.; Great Lakes v Statistics.; Great Lakes--Environmental conditions.
Genre Terms:
Great Lakes v Surveys.; Annual reports.; Pamphlets.; Manuals.; Directories.; Histories.; Newsletters.; Proceedings.; Bulletins.; Reports.; Videotapes.; CD-ROMs.
- Unit Publications
  The Unit Publications series (4.5 linear feet) contains printed material published specifically by the Michigan Sea Grant. These publications are defined as being widely distributed and may be published at regular intervals. They are arranged alphabetically by genre of the publication. Included in the unit publications are several different manuals that focus on risk management, confined water training, and homeowners guides that address environmental concerns. Several of the manuals focus on educators and outline projects geared towards children in 6-8th grades. Several editions of the Michigan Sea Grant newsletter titled Upwellings are also included in this series. Upwellings contains general information about recent projects and reports sponsored by the Michigan Sea Grant Program. This newsletter can serve as a good starting point for individuals interested in gathering a broad understanding of the goals, mission, and target areas of interest of the Michigan Sea Grant Program.
  The reports have retained the original organizational structure given to them by the donor and are arranged by their year of publication and publication number. These reports address a wide range of issues and could be used by individuals researching topics concerning land erosion, Grand Traverse Bay, scuba diving safety, wildlife, and environmental concerns. Many of the reports focus on pollution problems and discuss polychlorinated biphenyls and other chemical pollutants. Also included are reports that address economic concerns such as the fishing industry, Great Lakes shipping, petroleum, and boating.
  - Annual Reports
    - Michigan Sea Grant Program, 1971-1975, 1977-1981, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Michigan Sea Grant College Program 1982-1983, 2 folders (Box 1)
      [More recent annual reports are included as part of the newsletter Upwellings; separately cataloged EA 80 U71 U71]
    - People and Projects, 1979-1989 (Box 1)
    - People and Projects, 1989-1999 (Box 1)
  - Biennial Reports
    - Michigan Sea Grant Extension Biennial Report, 1985-1986 (Box 1)
    - Michigan Sea Grant College Program, 1997-1999 (Box 1)
    - National Sea Grant College Program, 1998-1999 (Box 1)
  - Evaluation Report
    - Michigan Sea Grant College Program 1988-1999 (Box 1)
  - Extension Bulletins
    - Marine Advisory Service 1976-1990 (Box 1)
  - Fact Sheets
    - Great Lakes Legislative Updates, 1-4, 1994 (Box 1)
    - Great Lakes Sea Grant Network: Congressional Briefing Book 1993 (Box 1)
    - Lakewide Management Plan (LAMP), 1992-1994 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous 1990-1997 (Box 1)
  - Flyers
    - Miscellaneous 1989, 1999 (Box 1)
  - Manuals
    - A Lake Trout Rehabilitation Guide for Lake Huron 1998 (Box 1)
    - Clean Marina Guidebook, 2004 (Box 1)
    - Coping with High Lake Levels: Homeowners Guide, 1986 (Box 1)
    - Hyperbaric Chamber-Attendants Handbook 1979 (Box 1)
    - Preparing for the Twenty-First Century: Program Guide, 1996 (Box 1)
    - Reporting on Risk 1994-1995 (Box 1)
    - Water and Land Resource Utilization Simulation (WALRUS 1), 1972 (Box 1)
    - Manuals for Educators
      - General 1979-1998 (Box 1)
      - Curriculum Project, Interdisciplinary Activities for Grades 6-8 #400, 1983 (Box 1)
      - Purple Loosestrife Project 1999 (Box 1)
    - Manuals for Instructors
      - Confined Water Training 1978 (Box 1)
  - Long Range Plans
    - Michigan Sea Grant College Program 1987-1988 1990-1995, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Michigan Sea Grant Integrated Research Program 1995-2001 (Box 2)
    - Strategic Plan 2000-2005, 2005-2010 (Box 2)
  - Newsletters
    - Diver Education Series, 1991-1992 (Box 2)
    - Surfbeat, undated (Box 2)
    - [Upwellings; separately cataloged; Call No: EA 80 U71 U71] (Box 2)
  - Pamphlets
    - Conditions of Award 1989-1999 (Box 2)
  - Pamphlets (cont.)
    - Educational 1973-2002 (Box 2)
    - Environmental Issues 1973-2003 (Box 2)
    - Great Lakes Sea Grant Network undated (Box 2)
    - Michigan Sea Grant College Program 1985-1999 (Box 2)
    - Site Reviews, 1982-1986 (Box 2)
    - Publications 1976-1982 (Box 2)
    - Publications Policy 1988-2000 (Box 2)
    - Recreation 1979-1994 (Box 2)
    - Sea Grant Week 1995 Summary Report undated (Box 2)
  - Proceedings
    - Michigan Sea Grant Retreat 1978 (Box 2)
    - Fishery Conference: Status of Chinook Salmon in Lake Michigan (CD-ROM) 2005 (Box 2)
  - Proposals
    - Michigan Sea Grant College Program: Volume III 1985-1986 (Box 2)
  - Reports
    - 1970
      - Annotated Bibliography of Scientific Information on Grand Traverse Bay, #201, 1970 (Box 2)
      - Shoreland Planning in the Great Lakes Basin and Selected Coastal Zones of the United States #202, 1970 (Box 2)
      - Interim Bibliography of Scientific Information on Grand Traverse Bay, #903, 1970 (Box 2)
    - 1971
      - Cave Diving: Equipment and Procedures, #10, 1971 (Box 2)
      - A Methodology for Mathematical Modeling of Biological Production, #202, 1971 (Box 2)
      - Evaluation of Input-Output as a Tool for the Study of Economic Structure of the Grande Traverse Bay Area, #203, 1971 (Box 2)
      - Grand Traverse Bay in the Great Lakes Basin, #210, 1971 (Box 2)
      - Research Diver's Manual: Underwater Operations Project, #212, 1971 (Box 2)
      - Current Meter Observations of the Circulation in Grand Traverse Bay of Lake Michigan: Mooring Methods and Initial Results, #214, 1971 (Box 2)
      - Diving Techniques Used in the Study of Ferromanganese Nodule Deposits, #300, 1971 (Box 2)
    - 1972
      - Grand Traverse Bay Water Quality Investigations, #103, 1972 (Box 2)
      - Evaluation of Methodology in the University of Michigan's Sea Grant Delphi Inquiry, #202, 1972 (Box 2)
      - Public Policy and Institutional Interaction Project: Great Lakes Survey Questionnaire, First Progress Report, #203, 1972 (Box 3)
      - A Description and Analysis of Coastal Zone and Shoreland Management Programs in the United States, #204, 1972 (Box 3)
      - Public Participation in Decision-Making, #206, 1972 (Box 3)
      - Steady State Modeling Program: Application Manual, #207, 1972 (Box 3)
      - The Evolving Role of the Federal Government in the Management of Lake Michigan, #209, 1972 (Box 3)
      - Oceanography Field Practice, #215, 1972 (Box 3)
      - A Hydrological Model for Estimating the Inflows to and Outflows from Grand Traverse Bay, #214, 1972 (Box 3)
    - 1973
      - An Investigation of the Meteorological Impact of Mechanical-Draft Cooling Towers at the Palisades Nuclear Plant: Progress Report 1973, undated (Box 3)
    - 1974
      - Shore Erosion Engineering Demonstration Project: Post-Construction-Season Progress 1974, undated (Box 3)
      - A Biological Production Model for Grand Traverse Bay, #200, 1974 (Box 3)
      - Environmental Decision Making in Industry, #201, 1974 (Box 3)
      - Air-Control-Communication Console for Surface-Supplied Diving, #204, 1974 (Box 3)
      - Surface Current Drifters: Evolution and Applications, September 1974 (Box 3)
    - 1975
      - A Food Web Model for Lake Michigan Part 2-Model Formulation and Preliminary Verification, #201, 1975 (Box 3)
      - Computer Simulation in the Analysis of Surface Current Drifter Data, #204, 1975 (Box 3)
      - Skin and Scuba Diving and Associated Rescue Techniques for Lifeguards and Water Safety Instructors, #601, 1975 (Box 3)
      - Water and Land Resource Utilization Simulation (WALRUS I): Revised, #602, 1975 (Box 3)
      - Research Diver Training Program, #603, 1975 (Box 3)
      - Coastwise Currents in the Vicinity of Chicago, and Currents Elsewshere in Southern Lake Michigan, [1975 ?] (Box 3)
    - 1976
      - Fishes of the Grand Traverse Bay Region, #100, 1976 (Box 3)
      - The Limnology of Grand Traverse Bay, Lake Michigan, #200, 1976 (Box 3)
      - Grand Traverse Bay Limnological Data, #201, 1976 (Box 3)
      - Buoyancy Compensation: Use or Abuse and Emergency Ascent Training: Safe or Unsafe, #306 and #307, 1976 (Box 3)
      - "It Won't Happen to Me" Syndrome: Preparation for an Emergency and Recreational Surface-Supplied Diving, #309 and #310, 1976 (Box 3)
      - Selected Limnological Data from Saginaw Bay, Lake Huron, #902, 1976 (Box 3)
      - Consumers' Perceptions of and Responses to the use of Underutilized Fish Species in Hot Dogs, #201, 1977 (Box 3)
    - 1977
      - The Michigan Demonstration Erosion Control Program in 1976, #200, 1977 (Box 3)
      - Guidelines for Preparation of Occupational Safety and Health Standards for Scientific/Educational Diving Operations, #204, 1977 (Box 3)
    - 1978
      - Petroleum Hydrocarbons and Heavy Metals in Great Lakes Surface Films, #202, 1978 (Box 3)
      - Profiles of Aquaculture in Michigan, #203, 1978 (Box 3)
      - Michigan Commercial Fishing Regulations: Summary of Public Acts and Conservation Commission Orders 1865-1975, #605, 1978 (Box 3)
    - 1979
      - Research Strategy for Recreation Sub-Program Michigan Institutional Sea Grant Program, #116, 1979 (Box 3)
      - Purse Seining on the Great Lakes: Vessels, Gear, and Operation, #200, 1979 (Box 3)
      - Life History, Abundance, and Potential Harvest of Carp from Michigan Waters of the Great Lakes, #205, 1979 (Box 4)
      - Bibliography of Coral Reef Fish Research, with Emphasis on Western Atlantic Families (Subject Index Included), #206, 1979 (Box 4)
      - The Effect of Sediment Oil Contamination on the Bioaccumulation and Excretion of Aroclor 1242 by Chironmid Larvae, #207, 1979 (Box 4)
      - Purse Seining on the Great Lakes: Catches, Efforts, and Problems, #211, 1979 (Box 4)
      - Acquisition of Public Access Sites to the Great Lakes, #214, 1979 (Box 4)
      - Petroleum Transport on the Great Lakes, #217, 1979 (Box 4)
      - Fishery Management: Goals and Tools, #505, 1979 (Box 4)
      - Diving Record and Qualification Book II, #602, 1979 (Box 4)
      - Management of Injuries Caused by Marine Organisms, #604, 1979 (Box 4)
      - Great Lakes Information: 3rd-11th Quarterly Reports, 1979-1981, 9 folders (Box 4)
    - 1980
      - Attitudes of a Scuba Diving Population Concerning Governmental Regulation of Underwater Resources, #201, 1980 (Box 4)
      - Lake Michigan Surface Films: Fatty Acids and Aliphatic Hydrocarbons, #202, 1980 (Box 4)
      - Environmental Controls on the Composition of the Surface Microlayer in Lake Michigan, #203, 1980 (Box 4)
      - Shipwreck vs. Nonshipwreck Scuba Divers: Characteristics, Behavior, and Expenditure Patterns, #205, 1980 (Box 4)
      - Hyperbaric and Undersea Medicine: Near-Drowning, #312, 1980 (Box 4)
      - Cold Water Near-Drowning, #316, 1980 (Box 4)
      - Ice Uplift on Piles on the Upper Great Lakes, #506, 1980 (Box 4)
      - The Use and Construction of Small-Mesh Trap Nets, #516, 1980 (Box 4)
      - The University of Michigan Manual of Safe Practices for Scientific Academic Scuba Diving, #600, 1980 (Box 4)
    - 1981
      - Model Great Lakes Commercial Fisheries Statute: Adapted for use in the State of Michigan, #200, 1981 (Box 4)
      - Surface Ship Path Control Using Multivariable Integral Control, #201, 1981 (Box 4)
      - Effects of Control Systems on Optimization of Ship Size for Navigation in Restricted Waters of the Great Lakes, #204, 1981 (Box 4)
      - New No-Decompression Tables Based on No-Decompression Limits Determined by Doppler Ultrasonic Bubble Detection, #205, 1981 (Box 4)
      - Observations on Low-Cost Shore Protection, #206, 1981 (Box 4)
      - Mathematical Evaluation of Multi-Level Diving, #207, 1981 (Box 4)
      - The Legal Rights of the Public in the Foreshores of the Great Lakes, #209, 1981 (Box 4)
      - Sawdust and Wood Chip Deposits in Near-Shore Lake Michigan Waters Near Manistique, Michigan, #211, 1981 (Box 4)
      - Preliminary Investigation of Spawning Habitat Conditions and Reproduction of Lake Trout in Eastern Lake Michigan Near Port Sheldon, Michigan, #213, 1981 (Box 4)
      - Fish in Lake Michigan, #600, 1981 (Box 4)
      - Pollution Problems of the Great Lakes Region: Conference Proceedings, June 9-11, 1980 #900, 1981 (Box 4)
    - 1982
      - Ice Strengthening of Great Lakes Bulk Carriers, #200, 1982 (Box 4)
      - Management Guidelines for Michigan's Great Lakes Bottomland Preserves, #201, 1982 (Box 4)
      - 1980 Michigan Recreational Boating Survey, #202, 1982 (Box 4)
      - Michigan Great Lakes Recreational Boating: Synthesis of Current Information, #203, 1982 (Box 4)
      - Economics of Sport Fishing in Alcona County, #204, 1982 (Box 4)
      - A Profile of the Michigan Commercial Fisherman, #205, 1982 (Box 4)
      - Feasibility of Moving Western Coal Through a Transshipment Point Located on Lake Michigan, #206, 1982 (Box 4)
      - Effects of Pentachlorobiphenyl on Growth of Nutrient Enriched Phytoplankton from Lake Michigan, #300, 1982 (Box 4)
      - Recreational Boat Owners' Response to Energy Constraints, #301, 1982 (Box 4)
      - Trends in Recreational Boating in Michigan, #302, 1982 (Box 4)
      - Great Lakes Shipping, Transportation and Markets for Michigan's Forest Products: A Preliminary Economic Inquiry, #500, 1982 (Box 4)
      - Grain Transportation on the Great Lakes-St. Lawrence Seaway, #501, 1982 (Box 4)
      - Aquatic Park Management: Symposium Proceedings, #900, 1982 (Box 4)
      - Bluff Slumping: Proceedings of the 1982 Workshop, #901, 1982 (Box 4)
    - 1983
      - Pressure Signatures of Great Lakes Bulk Carriers in Shallow Water and Restricted Channels, #200, 1983 (Box 4)
      - Economics of Sport Fishing in Muskegon County, #202, 1983 (Box 4)
      - Spending Patterns and Economic Impacts of Michigan Registered Boat Owners, #210, 1983 (Box 4)
      - Fractionation of Hydrophobic Organic Materials in Surface Microlayers, #301, 1983 (Box 5)
      - Enrichment of PCBs in Lake Michigan Surface Films, #302, 1983 (Box 5)
      - Is Great Lakes Shipping an Underutilized Economic Resource?, #500, 1983 (Box 5)
      - Assessment of Wetland Resources: Manual for a Workshop, #600, 1983 (Box 5)
    - 1984
      - Proceedings of the 14th International Conference on Underwater Education, November 1983, #300 to #304, 1984 (Box 5)
      - Applied Geography Conferences: Cognitive Maps of Tourism Regions, #311, 1984 (Box 5)
      - Microcomputers in the Boatyard
        - Advanced Boatyard Technologies, #600, 1984 (Box 5)
        - Microcomputer Basics, #601, 1984 (Box 5)
        - Microcomputer Operating Systems and Languages, #602, 1984 (Box 5)
        - Microcomputer Business Applications, #603, 1984 (Box 5)
        - Microcomputers and Production Control, #605, 1984 (Box 5)
        - Microcomputers and Design Aids, #604, 1984 (Box 5)
    - 1985
      - The Great Lakes Charterboat Fishing Industry: Workshop November 1985, undated (Box 5)
    - 1986
      - Age and Growth of Fish, #310, 1986 (Box 5)
      - Diver Education Series, #500 to #513, 1986, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - 1987
      - Institutional Arrangements for Great Lakes Management: Past Practices and Future Alternatives, An Executive Summary, #200E, 1987 (Box 5)
      - Institutional Arrangements for Great Lakes Management: Past Practices and Future Alternatives, #200T, 1987 (Box 5)
      - Microprocessor Applications to Multi-Level Air Decompression Problems, #201, 1987 (Box 5)
      - Diver Education Series, #501 to #504, 1987 (Box 5)
      - Behavior Patterns of Divers Visiting the Alger Bottomland Preserve, #505, 1987 (Box 5)
      - 1986 Recreational Diving Activity in Michigan Bottomland Preserves, #506, 1987 (Box 5)
      - A Profile of 1986 Diver Activity in the Thunder Bay Bottomland Preserve, #507, 1987 (Box 5)
      - A Profile of Great Lakes Diver Activity, Travel, and Expenditure Patterns, #508, 1987 (Box 5)
      - 1985 Michigan Charter Fishing Study, #509, 1987 (Box 5)
      - Community Enhancement of a Great Lakes Charterboat Fishery in Grand Haven, Michigan, #510, 1987 (Box 5)
      - Communicating Science to the Public, Mass Media and Science: Worlds at Odds?, #900, 1987 (Box 5)
    - 1988
      - Great Lakes Coastal Erosion Research Needs: Workshop Summary, #900, 1988 (Box 5)
    - 1989
      - Hybrid Water Law Systems: Would One Be Advantageous for Michigan?, #200, 1989 (Box 5)
      - Trends and Emerging Environmental Issues in the Great Lakes: Perceptions and Assessments, #201, 1989 (Box 5)
      - Size and Seasonal Variations of PCBs in Chinook Salmon Fillets from Lake Michigan near Ludington, Michigan, #202, 1989 (Box 5)
      - 1987 Upper Michigan Charter Fishing Study, #501, 1989 (Box 5)
      - Community Enhancement of a Great Lakes Charterboat Fishery in Grand Haven, Michigan, #502, 1989 (Box 5)
      - Results of the Sport Diving and Great Lakes Aquatic Parks Survey 1992, undated (Box 5)
      - Results of the Sport Diving and Great Lakes Aquatic Parks Survey: Executive Summary, #200ex, 1992 (Box 5)
    - 1993
      - An Analysis of the Development Needs of Michigan Bottomland (Underwater) Preserve Communities Using the Nominal Group Technique, #201, 1993 (Box 5)
    - 1994
      - Upper Peninsula of Michigan Lake Superior 1992 Transient Boater Marketing and Economics Survey, #204, 1994 (Box 5)
      - A Comparison of the Escanaba 1988 and 1992 Transient Boater Marketing and Economics Surveys, #205, 1994 (Box 5)
    - 1996
      - Chemistry, Temperature, and Secchi Disc Data for Hatchery Bay, Western Lake Erie 1996, undated (Box 5)
    - 1998
      - Rouge River Assessment 1998, undated (Box 5)
      - Rouge River Assessment Appendix 1998, undated (Box 5)
- Topical Publications (Box 6)
  The Topical Publications series (1 linear foot) includes printed materials published to document specific events or activities such as fund-raising or one-time conferences hosted by the Michigan Sea Grant College Program. The topical publications also contain recipe books, publications addressing boating, economic opportunities, environmental concerns, and a hurricane reconstruction initiative. In addition to the more general topical subjects there is a folder that contains a number of publications that address zebra mussels and other invasive species and their effect on the Great Lakes area. Visual material is also included in the Topical series, such as two VHS tapes addressing environmental concerns, and a CD-ROM documenting hurricane reconstruction in Nicaragua.
  - Boating (Box 6)
  - Economic Opportunities (Box 6)
  - Educational Sources (Box 6)
  - Environmental Concerns (Box 6)
  - Fishing (Box 6)
  - Hurricane Mitch Reconstruction: Nicaragua Assistance Program (CD-ROM), 2002, 1 optical disks CD-ROMs (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
  - National Marina Network Program 1997 (Box 6)
  - Recipes (Box 6)
  - Recreation (Box 6)
  - Zebra Mussels (Box 6)
  - Work Plans
    - Marine Advisory Program 1978-1979 (Box 6)
- Posters
  - Outsize Posters (Folder 1)
    (located at Bimu)
Related Material
Many Sea Grant reports are available on-line within the University of Michigan Technical Reports collection digitized by the University of Michigan Digital Library Production Service. The reports are available at the following URL (as of March 2004): http://www.hti.umich.edu/u/umr/